Preliminary Inventory to the Alonzo Bland Calder Papers, 1911-1956.
Hoover Institution Archives
Alonzo Bland Calder Papers,
1911-1956.
75007
Calder, Alonzo Bland, 1892-
45 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize box. (19 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Memoranda, reports, correspondence, clippings, photographs, and pamphlets, relating to American foreign and economic relations with China in the interwar period and immediately after World War II, and to American foreign and trade relations with the Soviet Union, Egypt and Malaya.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Access Points
Africa.; China.; China--Commerce--United States.; China--Foreign relations--United States.; Egypt.; Egypt--Commerce--United States.; Malaya.; Malaya--Commerce--United States.; Malaysia.; Soviet Union.; Russia (Federation); Soviet Union--Commerce--United States.; United States--Foreign relations.; United States--Commerce--China.; United States--Commerce--Egypt.; United States--Commerce--Malaya.; United States--Commerce--Soviet Union.; United States--Foreign relations--China.; United States. Dept. of State.; Diplomats--United States.
Biographical Note
1892 Born, Iowa
1915 Secretary to Jeremiah Smith, Jr. on relief mission to Turkey, Rockefeller Foundation
1916 Clerk, American Legation, Berne, and American Embassy, Petrograd
1917-1920 Petrograd, New York City and Shanghai in various capacities for W.R. Grace & Co.
1920-1922 Department of Commerce clerk, Peking; later, Trade Commissioner and Assistant Commercial Attache under Julean Arnold
1923-1926 Assistant Trade Commissioner, Tokyo
1926-1928 Trade Commissioner, Shanghai
1928-1930 Assistant Commercial Attache, Peking
1930-1939 Assistant Commercial Attache, Shanghai
1939-1941 Consul, Shanghai
1940 (?) Held in diplomatic custody by the Japanese until June 1942
1942 Repatriated and assigned to Moscow as First Secretary in charge of economic studies
1942-1943 Second Secretary and Consul, American Embassy, Moscow
1943-1945 First Secretary and Consul, Moscow
1945 First Secretary, American Embassy, Cairo
1945 First Secretary, American Embassy, Chungking
1945-1949 Commercial Attache, Shanghai
1952 Retired
Container List
- Correspondence, family, 1930-1940 (Box 1.)
- Biography
- Pamphlets and reports on China
- Shanghai Rotary Club handbook
- Correspondence, family, 1940's (Box 2.)
- The Shanghai Times, issues and clippings (Box 2.)
- Pamphlet by J. Stalin, Moscow, 1943 (Box 2.)
- 1940's bank statements
- Issues of 1939 Monthly Trade Report-China (Box 3.)
- Correspondence, family, 1930's
- "A Study of China's Financial Situation," submitted by Calder, Assistant Commercial Attache, and approved by Julean Arnold, Commercial Attache
- Private file, scrap and clipping book, Japan. Binder
- Correspondence, 1940-1950 (Box 4.)
- Clippings
- Storijec case
- Memoranda, 1940
- January 1952 Foreign Service Journal (article about John S. Service)
- Items for scrapbook
- Material for scrapbook (Box 5.)
- Correspondence, 1940-1950
- Clippings
- Rotary Club of Shanghai talks (Box 6.)
- Formosa, reports
- Calder's weekly reports as Assistant Commercial Attache, 1920's
- Reports on railways and aviation, 1920's
- Mantell's General Report and Recommendation on Chinese Railways, 1930
- Speeches
- Correspondence, 1945-1954 (Box 7.)
- Calder's personnel files, 1943-
- Foreign Service Office Class 4 certificates
- USSR identification card, 1945
- Family photographs
- Clippings, 1948-1955
- Correspondence, family and professional, 1944-1954 (Box 8.)
- Moscow apartment rent receipts, 1943-1944
- Intelligence Digest, December 1948, produced by Kenneth de Courcy. Also June 1951 and July 1953
- Bulletins, Diplomatic and Consular Officers Retired, Inc. (DACOR)
- Clippings, 1951
- Articles, bulletins, memoranda on China and commerce
- U.S. Department of Commerce Bulletins, 1925 (Box 9.)
- Monthly trade and economic reports on Japan, 1924, 1925
- American Chamber of Commerce reports and bulletins, 1927
- May 30, 1925, incident propaganda
- Correspondence, 1925-1929
- Issues: The Shanghai Evening Post, 1930; Shanghai News, 1951; others
- Textile Procurement in the Military Services, 1955, USGPO (Box 10.)
- Charges and Countercharges Involving...Senator Jose McCarthy...USGPO
- Salient Facts About China, by Julean Arnold, 1926. Pamphlet
- Speeches, 1926
- Correspondence, personal and business, 1918-1951, Includes Julean Arnold
- The Botanic Garden, The Sun Yat-sen Tomb and Memorial Park, Nanking, China.
- Address book. Pamphlet with diagram of garden and description
- Booklet of information, The American Company, Shanghai Volunteer Corps, 1917
- Calder family photographs (Box 11.)
- Album of pictures of factories in China
- Correspondence, 1932-1948
- Calder family photographs and pictures of the Calders in China (Box 12.)
- Correspondence, 1928-1957 (Box 13.)
- Speeches, 1926, 1928
- Pamphlets
- Unbreakable China; Coalition Government (Original copy from Yenan), by Mao Tse-tung, 1947 (?) (Box 14.)
- Clippings: Washington Post, New York Times, Singapore Standard, others
- Correspondence and memoranda, 1930-1955 (Box 15.)
- Speech material
- Weekly reports of activities, 1934-1937
- Clippings, 1932-1952
- The scrapbook of life for Rowland
- Diary, May 6-8, 1946
- Contacts, Chinese and foreign
- Chinese American Trade
- Congressional hearings: Security-Government Printing Office; Subversive Influence in the Educational Process; Transfer of Occupation Currency Plates-Espionage Phase
- Correspondence and memoranda, 1925-1955 (Box 16.)
- American Chamber of Commerce, Shanghai, correspondence and bulletins, 1927
- China in Chaos, North China Herald, April 1927; Bolshevik Activities in China; Some Documents Seized in the Soviet Military Attache's Office in Peking on April 6, 1927, American Chamber of Commerce Memorandum No. 13; two pamphlets by Chiang Kai-shek, April 1927; Manifesto to the People and Declaration to Kuomingtang Members
- Weekly Reports, 1927-1928
- Tariff reports
- Activities/Diary, 1926-1929
- Clippings on China-Japan controversy, 1931 (Box 17.)
- Sino-Japanese conflict clippings, map; Official Documents Relating to Japan's Undeclared War in Shanghai, Lowe Chuan-hua, compiler and editor, published by the Chinese Chamber of Commerce, Shanghai, 1932
- Soviet Russia bibliography; Sino-Soviet relations
- Speeches, 1928, 1931, 1936
- Weekly Economic Reports, 1937; Special Report No. S-52, February 15, 1940
- Weekly Reports, May-July 1935
- Maps of China, Japan, others
- Correspondence, memoranda, pamphlets, 1927-1941
- Correspondence, 1940-1956 (Box 18.)
- Correspondence with R. J. Phillips, 1926
- Institute of Pacific Relations hearings in U.S. Senate, 1952
- A Study of China's Financial Situation, by Calder, 1937
- Clippings, 1949-1952
- Correspondence, 1928-1951 (Box 19.)
- Pamphlets include: Mutual Security Agency, The Economic cooperation Administration (The Marshal Plan), 1950-1952; China's Fate and America's Future, by Julean Arnold 1940; Why Not Recognize Red China Now? by Ernest K. Moy, 1952; Report of the China-United States Agricultural Mission, Office of Foreign Agricultural Relations, U.S.D.A., May 1947 (Box 20.)
- Clippings, 1950-1954
- Congressional hearings: Communist Infiltration Among Army Civilian Workers; Communist Infiltration in the Army
- Correspondence, 1935-1954
- Correspondence, 1937-1952 (Box 21.)
- Pension data
- Tobacco (trade)
- Pamphlets include American Business With East Asia, by Gunther Stein, Institute of Pacific Relations, September 1947; Intelligence Digest, January 1951
- Soviets: Issues of Novosty Dnia, 1945, 1946; Novaya Zhizn
- Clippings, 1945-1951
- Correspondence, 1948-1952 (Box 22.)
- Road maps
- United Business Service Reports, 1953
- Log book, October 23, 1945-September 1947 (Box 23.)
- Letters from Nelle and Rowland, 1951 (wife and son)
- U.S. Senate Hearing, Special Senate Investigation on Charles and Countercharges Involving: Secretary of the Army Robert T. Stevens, John G. Adams, H. Struve Hensel and Senator Joe McCarthy, Roy M. Cohn, and Francis P. Carr, Par 40-Park 64
- Arnold, Mrs. Julean, letter about Arnold's suicide
- Miscellany
- Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1947-1953 (Box 24.)
- Father's letters
- Pamphlets
- Clippings, 1948-1951
- Calder's Desk File, 1918, a binder with photographs, issues of China Trade Bulletin, correspondence about products, trade, customs
- Address books (Box 25.)
- 1935 desk calendar
- Statements of account and correspondence with T. Bone, 1951
- Soviets. Includes Institute for the Study of the History and Culture of the U.S.S.R., Munich, 1953
- Correspondence, 1945-1952
- Pamphlets and miscellaneous
- U.S. Senate Hearing, Special Senate Investigation on Charges and Countercharges Involving: Secretary of the Army Robert T. Stevens, John G. Adams, H. Struve Hensel and Senator Joe McCarthy, Roy M. Cohn, and Francis P. Carr, Part 13-Part 20; Part 21-Part 39 (Box 26.)
- Study Group, U.S.S.R.
- Alonzo Bland Carter, August-October 1954
- Correspondence, 1918-1938 (Box 27.)
- Biography
- Miscellaneous notes, addressed, etc.
- U.S. Department of Commerce, Foreign Commerce Service, China Monthly Trade Report, January 1, 1932
- U.S. Department of Commerce, American Commercial Attache, China Monthly Trade Report, January 1927-January 1928; November 15, 1938; March 15, 1939 (Box 28.)
- Correspondence
- Clippings
- American Chamber of Commerce Bulletins, Shanghai, 1928
- Soviet Union
- Pamphlets and reports, including China Through the American Window, by Julean Arnold, 1932
- Private file of A. Bland Calder. Letters of commendation (Box 29.)
- Speeches and writings
- China Lobby
- Visitor's (business) cards, 1927. Two binders
- Personal file of Alonzo Bland Calder Speeches and special articles on China situation
- Congressional hearings on National and International Movements; Harold E. Talbott, Secretary of the Air Force (Box 30.)
- Subversion and Espionage in Defense Establishments and Industry; Joe McCarthy
- Diary 1933
- Correspondence, 1940-1955
- Clippings and pamphlets
- Study Group, U.S.S.R.
- Egypt, 1944, 1945
- Miscellany
- Correspondence, 1942-1953 (Box 31.)
- Miscellany
- Clippings
- Speeches and writings
- Telephone directory of Singapore and Johore Bahru, 1950
- China Annual Economic Report for 1937
- Monthly Trade Report, China, November 15, 1938
- Correspondence (Box 32.)
  - 1919-1930
  - 1923-1954
- Miscellany
- Clippings
- Pamphlets include Travel Diary of a Shanghai Editor: 1948, by Randall Gould
- Correspondence, 1919-1930 (Box 33.)
- Correspondence - Ethel, 1919-1923
- Speeches
- Lecture on the economy of the Soviet Union
- Speech, Kiwanis Club, Carmel, California, July 8, 1954
- Kohlberg, Alfred
- McConaughy, Walter
- Letters to reference people
- World Affairs Council, study group on U.S.S.R.
- Calder, personal, 1945-1948 (Box 34.)
- Miscellany, 1946-1947
- China and other briefings (commerce), 1946-1947
- Russian individuals and suspects, 1945-1949
- Letters to and from Nelle, 1945-1949
- Economic information on the U.S.S.R.
- Moscow papers (correspondence, 1943-1944)
- Clippings and pamphlets (Box 35.)
- Miscellany
- Correspondence, 1925-1952
- Egypt
- World affairs
- Schwarz, Ernest, Dr. and Dr. Bruce L. Canaga
- Matters to take up in the U.S. (Box 36.)
- Storojev, S.
- Correspondence, 1932-1948
- Digaut, M.
- Miscellany
- House at 593 Amherst Avenue, Shanghai. House No. 11, 1945-1947
- 1950 campaign to ungoof goofs (Chinese communism)
- M.W. Hudson's affairs (fund in trust)
- Stamps
- Meigs & Co.
- Christopher's affairs (James Christopher)
- Packing list
- Florida
- Formosa (Box 37.)
- European tour papers
- Representation allowance
- Rationing, food, consumer goods
- Scrapbook
- U.S.S.R. reports, clippings and pamphlet, XXV Anniversary of the Great October Socialist Revolution by J. Stalin, Foreign Languages Publishing House, Moscow, 1942
- Clippings, 1951
- Personal, 1942, 1951
- Schrifrin, G. 2 House, 366 Tunsin Road, Shanghai (Box 38.)
- Letters to be answered on vessel
- Pamphlet, clippings, 1945-1946
- Hong Kong, Calcutta, London
- Motor car documents
- Scroll (retirement 1952)
- Correspondence with Nelle, 1922-1923
- Department of State appointments, leaves, etc.
- Status - Bureau authorizations, salary, pay-cuts, etc.
- Inventory of household goods, insurance
- Accounts (Box 39.)
- Assets and liabilities
- Correspondence
  - General
  - B
  - Blanche
  - Bureau
  - C
  - Calder, A.B. (father)
  - Calder, Wilhelmina (mother)
  - Calder, Willard (brother)
  - H
  - Hall, Joseph
  - Kilham, George
  - M
  - S
- Miscellany
- Peking Work
- Slogan, mottoes, etc.
- Souvenir documents
- Switzerland
- Taxes, income
- Rugs
- Family photographs
- Retirement (Box 40.)
- Diet
- Correspondence, 1950-1955
- Carmel (California), 1952-1954
- Railways, Chinese
- Photographs
- News release material
- Pertinent sayings
- Status and salary
- Private papers
- Correspondence, Personal and miscellaneous, 1922-1950 (Box 41.)
- Lawrence's letters (Lawrence Tsang), 1950
- ECAFE (Economic Commission for Asia and the Far East), 1948
- Speeches and writings
- Alonzo Bland Calder's salary, etc.
- Appointment certificates
- Travel
- Travel orders for family
- Miscellany
- Grace Rowland correspondence, 1950
- Alaska
- Servants
- Coke file (Coca Cola)
- Singapore, 1948
- Travel to Tokyo
- Home leave 1948
- Inspector's report, Commercial Section, 1948
- List of reports and dispatches, 1946-1947
- Russian data
- Clippings, 1945
- Congressional committee hearings (Box 42.)
- Reciprocal trade agreements
- Briefing of VIPs. Includes Albert C. Wedemeyer
- Wedemeyer, Albert C.
- Annual report on Soviet Union, 1944
- Correspondence, 1918 (Box 43.)
- Speeches and writings
- Railways
- Hong Kong, 1947-1948
- Lawrence Tsang correspondence, 1950-1952
- Scrapbook
- Travel vouchers
- Miscellany
- Shanghai
- Soviet Union; Albert C. Wedemeyer
- China trade and industry (Box 44.)
- Household accounts, 1929-1948
- Invitations
- Singapore
- Shanghai; scrapbook (Box 45.)
- Miscellany
- Special reports, Japan, 1935
- Notes for reports
- Monthly trade and economic reports, Japan, 1926
- Personal
- Advertising matter to be dealt with
- Moore, Letters to
- Newspaper issues (Box 46.)
  - China Courier, July 13, 1927
  - China Mail, November 1, 1948
  - China Press
    - July 2, 1932
    - July 18, 1941
    - July 20, 1946
  - Malaya Tribune
    - May 27, 1949
    - June 30, 1950
  - Moscow News, May 1, 1943
  - The Municipal Gazette, July 1, 1932
  - The New Leader, March 8, 1947
  - Our Life. Nasha zhizn: Natsional'nyi nezavisimyi demokratich. Organ evr. (eiskoi) mysli, May 1946
  - Shanghai Evening Post
    - January 31, 1930
    - July 2, 1932
    - March 21, 1941
    - April 27, 1949
    - April 28, 1949
  - Shanghai News, July 17-22, 1951
  - Siberian newspaper, 1918, "purchased at a station by me en route from Petrograd to Vladiskvostok by 'get away' express. Trip took 33 days and nights."
  - South China Morning Post, November 1, 1948